Next up, uh, we have Alex Gablescu, who
is going to give us a talk on Battlelog
MD. And I've seen Battlelog MD a number
of times now, and I love I love these
sessions. Uh I I don't want to go too
deep into it, but uh sorry to cover too
much of what you're going to be saying,
but uh Alex Alex pretty much entirely
spec uh built this uh this this tool and
I love seeing an equivalent of Jira at
the ter at the terminal. I don't know
why, but it's just fun to see. Uh Alex
is going to show you how uh what you
know what backlog MD is and perhaps give
us some tips in and around how to build
uh through specifications and and and
what you know how we break down these
complex tasks.
Ladies and gentlemen, please give it up
to for Alex Gabillescu.
[applause] Thank you everyone for being
here.
Um, so you heard backlog MD a couple of
times today. Um, the reason is because
it's a very simple tool. Uh, it can
really help you uh being structured with
AI. And today we're going to have quite
a hands-on um if uh the internet works
very well. Uh we're going to actually
see backlog working live and how you can
actually implement a task for
uh using backlog MD. So uh let's start
from myself. So I am Alex Gavile. I'm a
lead developer uh in Vienna, Austria. I
speak Romanian, Italian, English. So
when you see me uh like at the coffee
break, you can talk with me in any of
these languages. I have more than 13
years of ex professional experience. Uh
and my main job I work as a uh withnet,
kubernetes, vjs.
But uh backlog MD was the the tool that
I created for me to learn AI and
actually uh it became so popular that um
yeah now I'm here I'm uh talking to you
about it and I hope you will like it. Um
so what are we going to do today? So I'm
going to uh give you some context how I
got to build backlog MD and why. Um then
I'm going to show you the tool and then
we're going to use uh backlog MD to
actually build the feature live
hopefully again if everything works fine
and uh some questions open questions at
the end of like what what is going uh
going to happen next and at the end you
will have the qu code to these slides.
So how I how did I start with AI? Um I
started with just prompting. Uh this was
when cloud code was launched. Um I tried
to uh give him tasks and uh achieve some
some good results and the results were
not so great. They were like sometimes
good, sometimes bad. It felt like really
playing with a slot machine and not
really having successful results. So
this uh gave me more or less 50% success
rate. And by success rate, I mean um
tasks that I eventually manage to
implement successfully and I don't have
to throw away the whole code. So even if
I have to go back and forth a couple of
times for me, that's still a successful
task. Uh then I discovered the agent
instructions cloud MD agents MD. This
was very very uh powerful for for me
that allowed me to tell agents how I
want the linting, the formatting, the
testing to happen. And you saw in
previous talks why this is very
important to have the AI agents iterate
until it uh knows it uh succeed and I
got to a more or less 75% success rate
and I was still not satisfied with with
the result. So I was trying to
understand what am I doing wrong and the
the answer was like I'm not doing that
many things wrong. I'm just like playing
around with the agents which are very
nondeterministic
and I need to find a workflow a process
that would put more determinist
determinism in in my work uh in in
[snorts] the coding. So how how did I
achieve this? So first I realized that
uh running out of context window would
like completely destroyed the the
quality of the work. So I wanted to
split my big feature into like smaller
tasks uh that can fit in a whole context
window and always tell the AI agent the
why are we uh building this feature. So
he has a it has a background like uh
understanding of why are we doing even
this feature the what and the how.
And um I realized it's even better if we
ask AI to create this information for
us. This sort of like specifications
from our description uh because this way
a feature that I describe like I would
like to have drag and drop functionality
in in my uh backlog MD uh will be
translated by AI into what AI
understands from my requirements. So
it's already like a feedback step uh
that is very important.
And something that comes from my
day-to-day work uh have a clear
definition of done. Uh how many of you
have a definition of done that is
written somewhere documented?
Okay. Some Yeah, I think if you uh you
should look into this. This is uh a
common approach to align with your
teammates uh when something is done and
what it means to be done. So like tests
are done, documentation is written, um
some ch like some put the task into some
state that means it's done and so on.
And with AI agents is also very
important.
So um the next step was to have these
tasks in uh markdown files. So I imit
initially uh had a huge markdown file
with all of the tasks. Then I realized
that the uh the agent will like get
confused by so many things at once. So
splitting into smaller markdown tasks
was like what uh made it make it work
much better. And I created um
um like a template for these tasks so
that I always uh have the same
information in all tasks and I can also
use the agent instructions to say to
tell the agent what to expect. So what
to actually check and what to actually
implement.
Um and the those markdown files will be
committed in git so that I can also like
go in cloud and say at task one to three
and then please um start working on this
task.
So this makes the loop more predictable
less nondeterministic.
uh at the very beginning the AI agents
would read the tasks directly from the
files. So it was perfect. They would
have to implement the acceptance
criteria and
few months ago cloud was really bad at
uh maintaining a clear uh scope of what
you wanted to build. it would either uh
say I'm done but it will not be done or
implement extra features that you never
requested and with uh the acceptance
criteria as sort of checkboxes cloud
would actually say okay I'm done and
only when the checkboxes are all uh
flagged
and with a clear definition of done in
the agent instructions uh I can actually
tell cloud or any AI agent you are you
can only say that you're done when all
of these things are done including
testing, linting and so on. So this
resulted in uh greater than 95% success
rate. I was very happy with the results
and it was almost done. So I could stop
there but then I wanted something more
uh I wanted more structure like a tool
around it and unfortunately Kio was not
launched back then otherwise I would
probably have uh not built back MD. uh
but I had to build it because I I there
was not much uh nothing else in in May.
So this is an image generated with nano
banana. Uh a few weeks ago there was a
trend uh take your software and tell
nano banana to generate uh an image of
how it would look uh if it would be like
a CD in a um delivered in 1995. And
actually if you think about a comban
board in a terminal this could actually
have been implemented in 1995. So I I
think this image fits and I will use it
from now on everywhere. And
this is um backlog MD. So this is the
cam board that runs in your terminal. Uh
it runs in your terminal but also like
in the slide deck. So this is live. So
um it runs almost everywhere because you
can run a terminal in a slide deck with
T-Mox. And what do you have here? You
have your comban columns. You have like
to-do in progress done. You can
configure the columns as with as many
columns as you want. In my case, I want
to keep it simple because most of the
times the picker task
works on it in few minutes or like maybe
1 hour and then it's done. So I don't
want to have too many status columns.
And here I have uh the possibility to
check the details of a task. So this is
uh how it looks with acceptance
criteria.
Uh
yeah. So uh this is like a t a task that
has been completed
and all of the acceptance criterias are
marked as done. So let me put back full
screen.
One sec.
Uh so why would you use uh backlog MD?
So uh this is not a replacement for G
linear or all of these very structured
tools. This is uh a tool that I made uh
for myself to work on my side project.
So it's something very simple but it's
as simple as uh getting good results
with it. And I think uh a lot of you at
least yesterday in the workshop told me
that you were very successful in in
getting good results. So I think this is
a good feedback and let me go back. So
uh what we're going to do today so uh in
uh the current board I don't have the
possibility to move tasks around. I can
just uh select a task and uh just see
the details. But what if I wanted to
move a task from to-do to in progress or
from in progress to done or like reorder
it? So I have my important tasks at the
top. So let's try to build it live. So
uh might be a bit challenging but let's
see if we if we can make it.
So before we can start uh it's very
important to know what we want to build.
So we need clear requirements
and in my case I would like to have a
new uh a button a command to toggle move
mode
and I want to see which task am I moving
and with the arrows up and down I will
reorder the tasks within the same column
and with left and right I will move it
between the status columns
and I can commit this change by pressing
M uh or enter or I can cancel and abot
and everything should return as before
we are pressing ask
uh and in the footer I don't know if you
noticed there are some uh instructions
how to use uh the current view so also
there we should see that we have this
new button available
right so [snorts] uh we have claude live
uh I just repeated here the the prompt
from the previous slide so hopefully if
this works yes he's He's connected. So
let's see what happens. So the first
thing that uh claude uh did uh it went
away. It read the backlog MD uh
workflow. So backlog MD is connected uh
to cloud via MCP and in the MCP I have
certain instructions
uh for for the agents how to use
backlog. So the first thing that it did
uh read how to how the whole backlog um
overflow worked and now if you just saw
it read the instructions for how to
create a task and then it run the soon
it will run the command to create the
task and the task is created. So so far
everything is fine. So uh it works. So
let's see the task.
Yeah I kn I knew this would happen. So
um
let me see
I will show you later at the end because
we have another step with the task. So
the task will be a markdown file uh with
certain sections. So there will be like
some metadata front matter there will be
a description and acceptance criteria
and at this point you can already review
if the agent uh understood your
requirement and proceed to the
implementation plan. The implementation
plan should be done right before you
start working on a task. So uh earlier
you could see in the uh to-do uh column
we had hundreds of tasks and we want to
check in a task, put it in progress and
create an implementation plan where we
tell we ask the agent to actually uh
come up with the plan. So what does it
mean? Understand the task requirements
uh from the description and acceptance
criteria.
check the documentation if we have any
documentation in the codebase
uh and come up with a plan to actually
implement the the feature. So let's have
code continue. So create an
implementation plan according to backlog
MD workflow for the task and fill the uh
implementation plan field in the task.
So while this is um proceeding u I will
explain few few other things. So how
does this process work? How do agents
know how to use backlog MD and why uh
they know immediately that what commands
to trigger? So uh I'm using MCP to again
to express this instructions.
The first instruction uh is about the
workflow in general like what is backlog
MD what the agent should expect from
backlog MD and then uh this is more like
a entry point where the agent is uh
being told hey if you want to create
tasks there will be task creation guide
if you want to uh work on a task there
will be the tax task execution guide and
when you think you're done please still
check the completion guide uh that gives
you some instructions of the definition
of done and some other important
information and then uh I'm also
exposing uh some tools um for managing
the tasks so that the AI agent can call.
So searching tasks, viewing task task
details, uh creating tasks and updating
tasks. Um in the workflow I usually tell
the agent to first search for an
existing task. So if I'm uh going to
work on uh for example move move mode uh
cloud will first search if there is
already a task about it if not is going
to create it and it works. So you you
saw earlier it's very successful. Uh
unfortunately the task is somehow the it
because it's very dynamic so everything
is happening live. Uh the slide didn't
pick up the task. So I will uh if we
have one minute at the end I will show
you exactly what Claude created. that
the task is there because we saw the
successful message
and the implementation plan should have
been uh at this point. And actually at
this point you have the most important
review step where you can see the the
specs plus the plan like the plan
represents the how and you as a
developer can verify if the agent is
going in the right direction. And at
this point, if everything uh is all
right and the plan to implement this
feature is correct, you can actually go
and ask the agent to to work on this
task.
So we want uh to have AI agents to write
the code for us. So pick any uh AI agent
that um that you prefer. So cursor,
cloud, codex, gemini, whatever. Um it
it's a nice to have if these agents have
MCP connection but if they don't there
is a fallback with using CLI commands.
CLI commands means just the agent runs
backlog task create backlog task edit uh
as you can also do from your terminal.
Uh but with MCP the agents have more
structured uh information about the
commands such as like this field is
required this field is optional and so
on. It's that's why I recommend usually
to use the MCP integration
and we want the agent to put the task
into done when it's really done.
So
um yeah let's see uh if we can actually
have the task implemented successfully.
So implement the task according to
backlog MD workflow. Usually you don't
have to say this. Just implement the
task should be enough. But for the sake
of like trying to not have problems
today, I I'm explicitly mentioning this.
So cloud is going to uh work for a
while. So in the meantime, let's go on
and have like a recap of what is backlog
MD.
So it's a CLI tool that both you as a
human and the agent can manage tasks and
that's it.
uh the actual implementation of the
tasks um happens by you going to the uh
cloud instance and asking a cloud or
whatever agents you use to actually pick
up a task and work on that task. So it's
not a sender center of command where you
can just delegate task directly to the
agents. It's it's really like a
JR/linear
uh in in your own repo and all of these
tasks are stored locally. So you can if
you wanted you can run backlog MD
completely offline as long as you have a
git repo on your computer and there is
also a web interface for who uh is
interested um back uh you you just have
to run black backlog browser and it's
going to spin up a local host uh web
interface with uh all of the tasks in a
nice web format.
So
let's recap what is Backlog MD.
It's an open-source uh CLI tool. It has
a terminal user interface, the one that
you saw earlier. Uh there is also the
web interface.
AI agents can interact with it uh with
backlog MD VS CLI or via native NCP
connection. It's crossplatform.
And the nice thing that I I uh I'm
getting uh told about Backlog MD is that
for people that just want some way to
structure their tasks. So I want to
build a small project and I already know
what I want to build and they want to
split this into smaller tasks. I don't
want to set up a GI account. I don't
want to set up databases or anything.
Just like backlog in it my repo and then
I start creating tasks either from the
CLI or I go to the AI agent and tell the
agent to create the tasks for me. So
it's it's very simple but it's very
effective and also I've been asked this
a lot. Yes, it syncs tasks between uh
branches. So if you and your colleagues
are working on the same repo, you would
see the tasks that other people create
in other branches as long as they push
to to some uh origin. Uh [snorts] and
this back backlog does it using git
commands under the hood. So it uses a
lot of git fetch and some other git
commands. So when you create a new task
and you push this to some uh
origin, other developers from your team
will see this as long as they fetch.
Actually they they don't even have to
fetch because backlog MD fetches uh
under the hood. So one of the uh only
requirements of backlog MD is to have
git uh command line installed.
And most important backlog MD was
written 99% by AI agents. This is
because first it was a challenge for me
to not write code and to not mix myself
with AI agents. I want to learn and to
get better at using AI. So every time I
had to do some adjustments, I asked the
the agent to fix everything for me. So
the only files that are really written
by me are the agent instructions.
Everything else is being written by AI
agents. Obviously I went back and forth
with some features. Sometimes I
completely cancelled. But what is good
about the backlog is that you have the
specs and if something goes wrong you
can go back to the specs and modify them
and start again on the same feature
maybe changing the agent and hopefully
this time it's going to go well. So now
if everything went right
we should see this
result. All right it's there. You can
see the move uh button there. So in the
meantime cloud has implemented the
feature that we wanted. So let me see if
it works.
So uh let's say uh the so first of all
implement move mode has been marked as
done. You can see it took few minutes.
Uh all of the acceptance criterias are
marked as done. We have the
implementation plan the one that we
couldn't see before. Uh we have
implementation steps and there should be
like at the very end here. Wow, Claude
really wrote a lot of information
implementation notes which is something
that I tell the agent to to write so
that we see um what has been done in
this task. So very quickly let's check
uh the result. So I press M task is
highlighted and I move it in progress.
Let's say something went wrong and it
didn't uh work as expected. Press enter
and it's here and I guess it's work.
Let's see. Yes, it's now in progress.
So, this is how you use backlog MD to
work on backlog MD or on any of your
projects. Um, all right. So,
let me conclude.
So, why does this work so well? So with
the markdown tasks uh you have more
chances to do better context
engineering. So to put exact information
as the agent needs from every single
task in in uh for the work to be done.
Uh you most likely will not run out of
context window if you work on one single
task per session. You can roll back
improve the specs and try again. Scope
is well defined with acceptance
criteria. agents don't do more or less
than expected because of the definition
of done. You have three steps of review
after the task is created after the
implementation plan is uh written and
after the code the execution so the code
review basically
and you can work on multiple tasks in
parallel maybe with git works.
All right. So very quickly open
question. So agile software development
will have to adapt for this AI native
workflows. So they have to uh you have
to integrate AI agents uh as team
members. So in in this case like using
backlog and is a good way to start but
it's obviously not what is going to be
there in a year. Uh you have to think
about story points estimations as
something that works with humans but not
with a agents that can run the whole
night and like finish a whole sprint in
a single night.
uh and then we have to like really know
what to build. We have to still uh get
the customer feedback and we need to
respond to changes and what are the
challenges. So automated reviews. So in
order to have a task being done and also
merge and deploy to production
solving conflicts, how many tasks we can
uh tackle in parallel and keep the
humans in the loop so that we deliver
good uh software products to other
humans. Thank you. Heat. Heat.
[music]